How do I practice compassion towards my
fellow beings according to the Buddhist
teaching?
>> Well, the Buddha didn't teach compassion
in a way of
uh
simply just
share uh
being affected by the fact that somebody
else suffers.
Like being kind of
moved by a loved one's uh difficulties,
for instance.
Because if that were compassion or if
that were what the Buddha taught, then
everybody would already have it.
So, it's a natural state.
What the Buddha mentioned as or advised
people to cultivate
was um well, first of all, metta,
which was uh absence of ill will or
friendliness. But the
But the
So, you have metta,
uh which is
friendliness, karuna, which is compassion, uh mudita,
karuna, which is compassion, uh mudita,
which is appreciation,
and upekkha, which is equanimity. And
all of the four were defined in a very
specific way that people usually ignore.
Which is
um
up, down, above, below,
left, right, in every direction,
boundless, uh with no exception,
uh with no exception,
having a mind that's free from enmity
and and uh aversion.
Uh so,
the difference between that and
the compassion that people usually talk
about is that the second one is biased.
It's like, you know, for instance, um
you you have a feeling of
affinity towards somebody,
you want to help them,
and in the process,
you're more often than not willing to
compromise the interests of somebody
else or something else.
So, for instance, your
whatever might be, a family member,
loved one,
pet, whatever it is,
whatever it is,
you would, for for example,
uh be willing to harm somebody in order
to protect them.
And it's by abandoning that that you
would So, you see, the problem isn't that you
So, you see, the problem isn't that you
don't have compassion towards anybody.
The problem is that you don't have
compassion universally.
In other words, there are some cases
where you are biased because of your
attachment. So,
So,
what you have to look into is not like,
"How do I choose
what people I can be compassionate
with?" Because anybody you choose is
almost certainly already going to be
precisely somebody who you don't need to
develop compassion before.
You need to look at the worst-case
scenario and imagine the things that
would actively incline your mind towards
hatred. And essentially develop a a mind where
And essentially develop a a mind where
you know that
it doesn't matter how unpleasant it
becomes, you will not start making those
uh
bi- you will not start acting out of
those biases.
So, that even if
the people who are most significant to
you are literally going to die,
uh you would still not
uh delight in the suffering of whoever
is going to kill them.
And that's not a a a thing that you
would do by
Because whenever you think about
individual people,
and it's it's a principle in mathematics
as well,
you can't reach infinity by adding
individual parts.
You can only like infinity can only be
covered by
by
encompassing the nature of something.
And the nature of the thing
that makes you not have compassion
is discomfort.
Like it feels unpleasant
in certain situations.
And whoever whoever or whatever is
whoever whoever or whatever is
responsible for that discomfort is
excluded from your compassion. So that is that
from your compassion. So that is that
exclusion is the problem.
It's not the lack of an inclusion.
Like so cuz you see that in the natural
state when you don't have anybody any
reason to hate someone
you're automatically interested in the
interested in their welfare.
So it's actually an act of exclusion
that occurs
because of the discomfort that you're
not developed in regard to
because of which your compassion is not
boundless. It's not because you haven't
chased after each individual person and
included them in the compassion.
It's because of that discomfort that
you're not trained in regard to. You
haven't uh
uh
sufficiently taught yourself
to not take discomfort as an excuse
for hatred or for um animosity.
>> So good one says, "Well, if one includes
oneself if one includes oneself in that
compassion." >> Well, you don't need to
>> Well, you don't need to
>> Or you don't exclude it. Let's put it
You don't exclude yourself. You would
actually realize that the
that compassion towards yourself would
be developing
yourself in regards to that discomfort.
>> Yeah, well, the thing is like
at the end of the day you are already
moved by your own feelings.
So it's like that's the one compassion
that you will not be able to to not
have. Um so
Um so
but I I see what you mean. Like you're
basically saying
it is about your own feelings.
But that is that is always the case.
Like whenever you would
uh be be kind of um
engage in protecting somebody
or hating somebody or whatever
it doesn't matter what political ideas
you hold. It's going to be because of
how you feel.
So
uh like you have to simply accept it.
Otherwise, there's no avenue for
development. To realize that
To realize that
uh
like all of these things I'm doing
all of these things I'm doing
whether it's uh
hating or trying to abandon hatred is
going to be because of how I feel.
Then through that avenue you can start to
through that avenue you can start to
see, okay, so all of this um
uh
reactions down the line of hating
not being compassionate, which is like a
a less coarse form of the same thing.
Um
all of that comes first from
the unwillingness to
just leave the discomfort be what it is
and not
um
have to defend yourself against it.
Because actually it doesn't make a
difference. Like
you it's not that you know, when you
kill someone
um
out of revenge
that it actually undoes
whatever bad thing was happening that
made you suffer to begin with.
It just makes you kind of feel satisfied
that it you did something about it, but
that's completely separate.
So it's it actually is pointless.
That when
uh
displeasure is occurring that you try to
defend yourself implicitly against it by
blaming it on somebody and and
excluding that person.
Cuz again, that is is action. The action
is the exclusion. You exclude the person
out of
the the
basis of friendliness or the basis of
compassion uh out of that discomfort. And like
uh out of that discomfort. And like
if you simply
uh
saw or dwelled
dwelt on that um
lack of need for that action, for that
exclusion, you saw how it makes no
difference and it actually makes the
problem worse.
Cuz you could see I Oh, I could actually
have this comfort there.
But I don't engage in all of these
actions of resisting it,
then why would it be a problem?
So I ironically you're making it worse
through the exclusion.
Because then that that is one of the
forms that craving takes.
Uh like unpleasant reaction towards
unpleasant feeling.
So
uh
I mean, it makes sense.
But the whole point is in those
uh
very sort of
acutely kind of like
kind of like
feels very very personal
scenarios where it's like the last time or it's
where it's like the last time or it's
it's
it's when you least want to think
about how you shouldn't exclude that
person from your compassion cuz like
it's you know, the worst imaginable thing
you know, the worst imaginable thing
they did to you.
That's when you need to
uh not try to to
cultivate these these uh rosy thoughts
of which is ultimately artificial. It's
like it you're holding that structure up
and it's going to fall as soon as you
stop it.
What you have to do which is actually a
form of samadhi which by definition has
to be effortless
is to undo
that uh impulse
of excluding the person.
Like again, it's it's a natural thing
to to not want somebody else to suffer.
You only start wanting that
as a coping mechanism
in regard to your discomfort.
So, if you stop that coping mechanism by
reflecting on its
pointlessness, for instance, you will
automatically stop the action of
exclusion. And that's how by abandoning that
And that's how by abandoning that
gratuitous sense of of
um gratuitous attitude of resistance to
discomfort, you would know that you have
included everyone automatically.
Because the only you would never
conceivably hate someone or have or any
type of animosity towards someone,
unless it's because of some kind of
displeasure that they caused on you.
So, you would know that in that way I
have covered the entire world, up, down,
above, below, universally,
you have abandoned the will
through one
thing, basically.
Through one gateway,
you have included the entire world.
>> Which is your resistance towards
feeling. >> Yeah. So, basically, the
>> Yeah. So, basically, the
each of the four Brahma Viharas
has its own opposite.
And then and the Buddha mentioned it in
one Sutta.
And each of those four
are really actions that you do, like
they're mental actions, of course,
that you do in response to displeasure.
So, the only thing you have to do to
cultivate, for instance, metta, which is
the first step,
is see that ill will is an activity that
you do
in order to try to shelter yourself from
displeasure. It's kind of adding this noise there
It's kind of adding this noise there
that supposedly, through some magical
thinking, will make the displeasure not
be there.
But it never does. Like, you just add
more noise
to the same room, and the other noise is
still there.
So, you realize, actually, if I don't
engage in this,
it's actually
less of a burden.
And both for myself and for everybody
else. And that's how you purify your mind from
And that's how you purify your mind from
your world. Like it has to be clear
that that principle
as a
uh in its nature
is perilous, pointless, uh
does not benefit anybody, not even you.
And that's the only way you would
abandon it in every possible instance.
Whereas the what people usually do,
which is
force yourself to love someone,
that has nothing to do with the problem.
If you
uh let's say you were born you were
somebody who every single person you met
in your life
uh you loved or you were in good terms
with. Like you never met somebody who
who uh made you actually hate them.
Well, as long as you're alive
and you have things that are pleasing to
you and things that are dis- displeasing
to you,
uh you will be capable of hatred.
So, it's just a matter of you not yet
having met
somebody who would have set you.
So, essentially what what or some
situation in which you would be upset.
So, what people are basically doing when
they try the supposed meta practice
loving kindness as it's called nowadays,
is just putting yourself in that state
where like circumstantially I'm in a
good mood towards everyone.
But there's always going to be some
unforeseen event
that you haven't accounted for because
that's the nature of things. It's
infinite, the range of possibilities.
And that's going to disturb you now like
when it comes. So, it's never going to
be boundless.
That's what I meant when I said before
like you can't reach infinity by adding
individual parts.
So, that gateway
is that action of resistance.
Like, you have to recognize that's an
action, a mental action that I engage
with when the unpleasant feeling presents
when the unpleasant feeling presents
itself. I decide
not as a super explicit choice, but it's
something that I could not do
to to explore and dwell on the details
of these
aversive perceptions of like,
perceptions of like,
you know,
the negative
think qualities of somebody, since and
how much of a fool they are, and
you you stop yourself from doing that
when there is the pressure to do so
because of the displeasure.
And that by doing that, you're training
your mind in meta.
So, when you abandon that activity in all of
when you abandon that activity in all of
its forms,
what you will be left with
is the more natural state where, you
know, imagine you you see somebody on
the street for the first time, and
there's nobody um
there's no reason for you to hate them.
There's no reason for you to love them
either cuz you know nothing about them.
But, if that person
like you would
it would be inconceivable to to
out of the blue
uh start wishing them harm.
You would wish them well if there was
any um
kind of
thought about that person,
it would not be a thought of harming
them. So, you that's what you would be left
So, you that's what you would be left
with in regard to the whole world
if you were to abandon that action of
ill will,
which is what obstructs the more
fundamental attitude of friendliness.
And that's why it evolved, the whole
thing evolves or culminates
in an even more fundamental attitude of
uh equanimity,
which is not caring.
It's not a
uh super refined form of care
that like when they people confuse the
metta so that is like a
a mother protecting her own child that
you should treat all beings.
Whereas the clear meaning is that's how
you would protect your own mind of metta
like a mother would protect her own
child. In other words, it's not about
being involved with the welfare of other
beings. It's about It's about
um
being very
uh vigilant
not to not to let your mind not to let
yourself engage
in these uh pathways
of resistance.
And then the more you do that, the less
involved with anyone you will be and
that's the uh equanimity.
The most refined and highest of the
Brahma viharas.
>> So that's uh
what is a certain state of non-care or
care-carefreeness? >> Not Yeah, not caring.
>> Not Yeah, not caring.
>> Yeah, not caring.
>> Which some people might associate with
like callousness.
But that's an activity. When you're
callous, it's because you
kind of intentionally decide to dismiss
something you could have
thought about like you you out of
resistance to the effort or whatever,
you decide not to think about it.
But that's not equanimity. Equanimity is
like I actually don't care.
It's not that I'm cared to the extent of
dismissing it. It's like the care does
not arise in the first place.